For example, how much do you work per
сколько вы вот например работаете в
day, yes, how many hours?
день в день да сколько часов
Yes, I work 10 to 11 hours,
Да я по 10 по 11 работаю
but in Europe If you worked 11
вот а в Европе Если бы вы работали 11
hours Yes, the employer would be fined, yes
часов Да работодателя оштрафовали бы да
Yes, it’s not me who asks sometimes for so many hours
Да не я сама прошу иногда столько часов
Why Because you need money Yes
Почему Потому что тебе нужны деньги Да
yes  because look because I
да потому что смотри потому что Я
understand Because some people work
понимаю Потому что некоторые идут на
two or three jobs Yes, in order to
две-три работы Да чтобы
survive Hello Don’t switch
выжить Здравствуйте Не переключайтесь
Let’s talk
Давайте пообщаемся
normally okay okay my friend is joking
нормально хорошо да ладно подружка шутит
with you, yes you are 18 years old  yes 19
с вами смот да вам по 18 лет есть 19
got it I’m from the city of Khmelnitsky, Ukraine You’re
понял Я из города Хмельницкий Украина Вы
from Russia, where you’re
из России
from Moscow And you came from
откуда Москва А по наехали откуда
Voronezh, because I see a provincial
Воронеж потому что я вижу провинциальный
dialect, her last name is Avdienko Well, in short,
говор у неё фамилия Авдиенко Ну короче
some provincial girls came to
провинциалки какие-то приехали в
Moscow, of course, yes, I understood And that they came to
Москву конечно да понял И что приехали в
Moscow and immediately understood the flag, yes  let's
Москву и сразу флаг понял да поддержим
support support
поддерживаем
support super then you have
поддерживаем супер тогда вам
a heart Well, yes, only guilty, apparently
сердечко Ну да только провин видимо
you're not provincial, cool girls
те вы не провинциалки классные девушки
That's how it turns out, yeah
Вот как получается перебувае да
they change their shoes right away I changed my shoes Yes, I thought
переобувают сразу переобулся Да я думал
you were so aggressive somehow I thought Everything Not
вы так агрессивно как-то Я думал Всё Не
I thought you, on the contrary, should also be there
я думал вас наоборот тоже надо там
somehow or what, I see you’re not
как-то там или что смотрю не вы
normal, so I don’t need to understand No, we are
нормальные значит не надо понял Нет мы
very good who you
очень хорошие кем
work for Sales Consultant It’s you who are
работаете продавец-консультант Это вы
shopping now  No, I’m at
сейчас магазинчики Да нет это я сечас
home right now and this is from the store
дома а это из магазина
Yes, I’m studying to be a dental
Да я учусь на зубного
technician
техника
Cool Well, yes, but I liked
Прикольно Ну да но мне больше нравилось
working at Gloria Jeans more, but
в Глории Джинс работать а как считаете
whose
чей
Crimea do you think is Ukrainian?
Крым украинский
Adin Ilinka  what does he
Адин илинка как
think? I think
считает Я считаю
that Yes, I don’t understand politics,
что Да я не разбираюсь в политике
you know, I’m not, I’m honest, honestly, no
понимаете я не вот я честно честно без
jokes. I don’t understand anything at all.
приколов Я не понимаю вообще
Okay, then I
ничего Окей давай тогда я с Провинциалка
won’t talk to Provincialka, I’ll talk to you. Come on,
не буду говорить с тобой поговорю Давай
come on. What’s your name Vika Vika, you’re
давай Тебя как зовут Вика Вика ты
great, you have a clear position  That’s
молодец у тебя чёткая позиция Вот потому
because the Girlfriend immediately started Oh, I don’t know that it’s
что Подружка сразу начала Ой не знаю там
all about fooling around And you’re
что всё придуриваться А ты
great No, well, what did I communicate with
молодец Нет ну а что мне общалась с
the guys just from Ukraine, that’s how my
ребятами просто с украино мне вот как
parents told me  I’m not saying
родители рассказали Я же не говорю
Look, you’re already an adult Look, you’re already
Смотри ты уже взрослая Смотри ты уже с
doing things with a guy What What kind of guy Well with
занимаешься Что С каким парнем Ну с
some Well, you have a boyfriend, after all,
каким-то Ну есть У тебя парень всё-таки
it’s like he’s not a boyfriend anymore There was once a
вроде уже не парня нет был когда-то
boyfriend No I didn’t have a boyfriend and the
парень Нет у меня не было парня а
girl didn’t have a girlfriend  I understood Well, why
девушка не было девушки понял Ну да куда
talk about politics with you then if
с тобой о политике тогда говорить если у
you have You? Yes, really, not
тебя Ты ещё Да действительно не
even printed out. Yes, I really really
даже Да действительно действительно
understood. And you already had a boyfriend, and you
понял А у тебя был парень уже да
see, she has a boyfriend, she talks about
видишь у неё есть парень она всё шарит о
politics all the time. She’s already an adult, she understands
политике Она уже взрослая понимает
the world, yes. And you  play the fool, you
мир да А ты придуривайся ты всё
understand everything, you just don’t want to talk No,
понимаешь просто не хочешь говорить Нет
she understands, I’m telling
она Она разбирается я же говорю Она
you, she understands just on purpose No, well,
разбирается просто специально Нет ну мне
what they told me, they told me that Russia
что сказали мне сказали что Россия
handed Crimea over to Ukraine and then decided to give it
передала Крым Украине а потом решила его
back dadada, it’s there and, as if purely
обратно дадада это есть и как бы чисто
legally, of course it seems as if
юридически конечно кажется как будто
Russia-  then
россия-то
a little to the edge Yes, but as if initially it was
немножко в край Да но как бы изначально
whose Crimea was Let's play No yours yours they
чей Давайте поиграем Нет ваш ваш ваш вам
gave it to you it's yours everything Come on Let's
его отдали он ваш всё давай Давайте
play this game, it's interesting I'll
поиграем в такую игру интересно я буду
ask a question And you'll both answer
задавать вопрос А вы будете обе отвечать
and I will  I’ll tell you who got a point for
и я буду говорить кто получил балл за
this question, let’s let’s Okay, let’s do
этот вопрос давайте давайте Хорошо давай
that,
давайте так
no, so let’s mean My name is Andrey,
нет так давайте значит Меня зовут Андрей
your name is
вас как
Vika Elizaveta Eliza, your name is Nastya Okay, okay, the
Вика Елизавета Елиза зовут Настя Ладно
first question is who should
хорошо первый вопрос кому должен
Crimea belong to the people so
Крым людям так
the people so zero points for each half of the
народу так по ноль баллов каж половина
population of Ukraine Oh, not Ukraine  And Crimea
населения Украины Ой не Украины А Крыма
Everything Wait just one more time how you are always
Всё Подожди просто ещё раз как вас посто
correct
ня правильно
so far zero points each so Next
пока ноль баллов каждый так Следующий
question who is to blame for the fact that Russia
вопрос кто виноват в том что Россия
attacked
напала на
Ukraine
Украину
government So you say What kind of
правительство Так ты говоришь Какое
government
правительство
Nastya  whose government of
Настя чьё правительство
the country Well, since Russia attacked, it means Putin
страны Ну раз Россия напала значит Путин
attacked So correct, one point Nast and
напал Так правильно один балл наст и
one point Vika oh everything is so second third
один балл Вика о всё так второй третий
question What needs to be done to stop the war
вопрос Что нужно сделать чтобы война
so all Trump has already been elected
прекратилась так всё трампа уже избрали
now he he won’t
сейчас он он ничего не
do anything Vika one
сделает Вика оди
point Nastya but points So  Vika has two
балл Настя но баллов Так что у Вики два
points, Nastya has one, while Vika wins
балла у Насти один пока Вика выигрывает
by one point,
на один балл
so the
так
question is, why does Russia sell
вопрос почему росмет
oil and diamonds? But people live
нефть алмазы Но люди живут
poorly because they steal a lot, and Nastya,
бедно потому что воруют много а Настя
what will she say? Well, what? Well,
что скажет Ну да Что Ну
yes, I agree, I understand  Well, you understand that you
да я согласна понял Ну ты поняла что
need to get Vikina’s points Yes, so
нужно добивать баллы викины Да так по
one point for each Vika has three points
одному баллу каждому у Вики три очка У
Nastya has two points
Насти два очка
okay yes Dasha Dasha’s question
окей да Даше Даше вопро
How do you feel Do you think there
Как вы относите Как вы считаете на
is
Украине есть
Nazism in Ukraine I think yes I think Yes there is Yes there is
нацизм я думаю да я думаю Да есть Да
definitely there but in  A small degree of a
определённо есть но в Малой степени
small part but points Nastya zero points
малой части но баллов Настя ноль баллов
Vika so
Вика так
far Well,
пока Ну
read, look at Nazism In Ukraine there is no,
почитаете смотри нацизма В Украине нет
maybe
может
there is, but there is no Nazism, that’s it And that’s all I don’t
есть но нацизма нет это такое А всё Я не
understand yes  Understand Well, you see, they didn’t understand
поняла да Поня Ну видишь не поняли
the question, like they never understood, but the
вопрос как что никогда не поняли но
answer is already there, so the question is you
ответ уже есть так так вопрос Вы
put it wrong, oh, the score is 3:2,
неправильно постали ой счёт 3:2
okay, the question is oppressed
хорошо вопрос утесняемый
[applause]
[аплодисменты]
there is
там
oppressed
утесняемый
Vika,
Вика
I don’t remember, well, why, according to the media, mo Vika
м я не помню ну я почему по СМИ мо Вика
Vika, I understood Vika  what do you say? Come on,
Вика я понял Вика ты что скажешь Давай
think a little,
думай мало
displace them, they took away one point for Nastya, zero
вытеснять сняли так один бал Насти ноль
points for Viki, not
балл Вики не
oppressed
утесняемый
in Russian, who wants, and so the score
по-русски Кто хочет Да так счёт
is evened out  3:3 damn this Battle is interesting
сравнялся 3:3 блин это Баттл интересный
I thought Vika would win now and it’s not so
Я думал Вика сейчас выиграет а не так
easy to see Nastya is also crying,
просто видишь Настя тоже рыдает мне
just an acquaintance told me that Ute was really taken off
просто знакомый говорил что Уте сняли
Uh-huh I see, so the question is who
реально Угу Поня так вопрос кто
shelled Donbass for 8 years
обстреливал 8 лет Донбасс
so Civilian it was not Civilian
так Гражданская же была нет Гражданская
Yes so zero points and Vika and  zero points,
Да так ноль баллов и Вики и ноль баллов
more details about what year Russia
мо поподробнее поб вчем году Россия
attacked Ukraine, capturing Crimea, Donetsk and
напала на Украину захватив Крым Донецк и
Lugansk, and since then there has been a War, yes yes And
Луганск и с тех пор идёт Война да да А
we’re talking about something else Well  so they tell you that it
нам про другое Ну вот вам говорят что
seems like there was a civil war in Ukraine
вроде как в Украине была гражданская
Yes, it’s kind of interesting, I
война Да какая-то интересно я по
watched an
телевизору смотрела
airplane on TV Tanks and she was with some people
самол Танки и она с какими-то людьми
who didn’t have planes with tanks Yes, she fought for
которые без танков самолётов Да воевала
8 years, well, it’s funny, it’s
8 лет ну это же смешно
true, it’s not for us how they present it to us, they
правда не нам как это преподносят нам
present it to us  civil war Russia is
преподносят что гражданская война Россия
now such a
сейчас такая
master of Gan and Donets who fought with whom in the
осво Ган и Донец кто с кем воевал в
civil war who fought with whom in the
гражданской войне кто с воевал в
civil war
гражданской войне
Yes who with whom Well look
Да кто с кем Ну вот Украина смотри
Ukraine Ukraine has tanks Airplanes Yes Air Defense A  with
Украина есть танки Самолёты Да ПВО А с
whom she fought just with people without
кем она воевала просто с людьми без
weapons Well, there were some kind of wars
оружия Ну там какие-то войнушки были
between each other Well, what kind How can you fight
между собой Ну какие Как можно воевать
without weapons Well, that too, yes, well, that is, there
Без оружия Ну это тоже да ну то есть там
was Russia, Russian troops just
была Россия российские войска просто так
said that for you Okay, so bye 3-3
для вас говорили О'кей так пока 3-3 у
we have a good
нас хорошо
uh
ээ
question kkkkk
вопрос ккккк
who should
кто должен
uh lead Russia after the death of
э-э возглавить Россию после смерти
Putin, but I don’t
Путина я а вот не
know And when he dies
знаю А когда он умрёт
soon it’s already there Everything has already been decided without
скоро так там там уже Всё решено уже без
us wrong answer Medvedev not the
нас неправильный ответ Медведев не
right answer no one because  Russia
правильный ответ никто потому что Россия
will disintegrate
распадётся
into an independent state So,
на независимое государство Так что вам
damn
по нулям блин
the question for you, do you think America is to blame
вопрос Как вы считаете Виновата ли
for the fact that Russia attacked
Америка в том что Россия напала на
Ukraine
Украину
America Well, America
Америка Ну Америка же Украину
supports Ukraine Well, is America to blame for
поддерживает Ну Виновата ли Америка что
Russia attacking
Россия напала на
Ukraine
Украину
perhaps Vika what are you saying No Vika
возможно Вика ты что говоришь Нет Вика
one point
один балл
A  you are zero, how can America be
А тебе ноль как может быть Америка
to blame for Russia since it attacked, then it is her
виновата Россия раз напала то она
fault, so who knows what someone
виновата так кто знает что кто кому
rustled in someone’s ear there Well, it was somehow strange
шуршал там на ушко Ну как-то странно
to violate such a question, so we have
было нарушать так вопрос так что у нас
4-3 so far  favor Vicki
4-3 пока в пользу Вики Давайте до семи
Let's play well until seven points until seven points
очков будем играть хорошо до семи баллов
Okay
О'кей
uh What do you think in Russia
ээ Как вы считаете в России
uh
ээ
because people are against the war
за то что люди выступают против войны
they go
идут
uh there with posters against the war they are
ээ там с плакатами против войны их
detained and put in
задерживают садят в
prison Yes we had
тюрьму Да у нас было
that Yes Nastya yes y  we were like this Well, yes, it
такое Да Настя да у нас было так Ну да
seems like one point at a time That’s it Okay 54
так по одному баллу каже Вот это Окей 54
so on Well damn until now it’s an
так дальше Ну блин до сем сейчас интрига
interesting intrigue because how do you feel about
интересная так как вы относитесь к
Zhirinovsky who
жириновскому который
lived as a carbon monger and
жил угарный чел просто и
that’s all  Well, he doesn’t know. I think
всё Ну он не знаю Мне кажется он
he’s smart, he foresaw a lot, yes. So Vika, he knows Vika’s history, he’s a good politician, maybe he’s a little conflicted, noisy, but he knows his clarify Vika’s position according to Zhirinovsky, he’s an intelligent person, but
Вика по жириновскому он умный человек но
a little bit conflicted, again, I have
немножко опять же конфликтный я к нему
such a neutral attitude towards him, I don’t  I can definitely
так нейтрально отношусь я не могу точно
answer you. Let's So do you support
ответить ты Давайте Так вы поддерживаете
Zhirinovsky or not? Like
Жириновского или не поддерживаете Вот
this To make it easier about Ukraine
так Чтобы проще было по поводу Украины
that he made statements in general in general in
что он высказы вообще вообще
general I yes
вообще я да
yes zero points each And what he
да ноль баллов каждый А что он
expressed is possible He  In general, he
высказывал можно Он вообще ВС он
said that they should only give birth, in
высказывал что должны только рожать
short, there. Well, no, I’m saying, again,
короче там А ну это Нет я говорю опять
he’s a fuss. He’s all about politics. We’re talking
же он угар У него вся про политику Мы
about politics, so it’s politics, he said,
про полити так это политика он говорил
and that it shouldn’t work at all, it
да что вобще не должна работать она
should, in short, yes. And you say, like, I didn’t
должна короче да А вы говорите типа не я
say that  I initially said that he was
говорила я изначально сказал что он
a carbon monger, he said that she should sit
угарный он говорил что она должна сидеть
and give birth only to this, because a woman can’t
и рожать только это Потому что нельзя
not go into politics because he
женщину не в политику потому что он
said yes, I know that, yes, they know that
говорил да это я знаю да знаеш они что
he
он так
said that, so far this question Let’s So
говорил так пока сй вопрос Давайте Так у
our score is 54 damn
нас счёт 54 блин
[music]
[музыка]
So interesting
так
Hmm What do you think is the best standard of
Хм Как вы считаете где лучший уровень
living in the USA or in Russia in the
жизни в США или в России в
USA the standard of living is
США уровень жизни - это
like In general, this is how you think a visa
как В целом вот так как ты считаешь виза
think about it I seriously don’t influence
подумай Я те серьёзно гово не влияй на
her choice
её выбор
Well, I didn’t live in the USA  I know how they are
Ну я не жила в США е я знаю как они там
not there There are a lot without there also have their own
же нет Там много без там тоже есть свои
mine mine Yes but Vika weighed the minus of ska
мину мину Да но Вика взвесила минус ска
USA you Weigh in the minuses and tell
США ты Взвесь в минусы и скажи
me where I don’t like the USA because I
где мне не нравится США потому что я
choose Russia  I don’t like it
выбираю Россию не люблю
I live in Ukraine Yes, but if someone asks me
Я живу в Украине Да но если меня спросит
Where is it better to live in Russia or the standard of
Где лучше жить в России или уровень
living in Ukraine or in the USA, I will of course
жизни в Украине или в США я конечно
say the standard of living in the USA is higher, so you
скажу уровень жизни в США выше вот ты
also choose Russia as I choose
тоже выбираешь Россию как я выбираю
Ukraine, but I’m asking you where the
Украину но вот тебя спрашиваю где вышей
standard of living is higher in  USA or in
уровень жизни в США или в
Russia, can I google statistics
России можно я загуглю статистику Я же
I don’t know Okay, time waiters
что я не знаю Ладно время официанты
earn more So you understand that they
больше зарабатываю Так вы понимаете что
earn more there, but there are
там же зарабатывают больше но там и
more taxes the answer was accepted by Vika plus point Nastya
больше ответ принял Вика плюс балл Настя
zero Oh no So that means  Vika it turns out 6
ноль О нет Так значит Вика получается 6
64 So Now there may be a last
64 Так Сейчас может быть последний
question Maybe there won’t be a last
вопрос Может может и не будет последний
question
вопрос
so look Vika about taxes I’ll just
так смотри Вика насчёт налогов просто
say Yes, if you get
скажу Да если ты в Калифорнии получаешь
12,000 dollars there in California Yeah, yeah, I don’t know
там 12.000 долларов Угу да то я не знаю
what you need And what do you spend
какие тебе нужно И на что тратить ты
such amounts on  In Russia, they won’t get it in
такие суммы в России да не получат за
six months, you know.
полгода понимаешь
Well, they cost a cup of coffee the same as us. Well,
Ну у них стоит чашка кофе как нас Ну
look at
смотри
the phone, look at how much
телефон смотри сколько вот зарплата у
your salary is, Vic, here it comes out for me, for example, in
тебя Вик вот у меня выходит например в
general,
целом
the salary is
зарплата
36 salaries without advance payment. Well  so for a month
36 зарплаты без аванса Ну так за месяц
3637 per month that is 360 dollars yes Well
3637 за месяц то есть 360 долларов да Ну
36,000 yes that is look Yes it is in
36.000 да то есть смотри Да это по
dollars 360 That is, what do you need Yes That is,
долларах 360 То есть тебе что Да То есть
you don’t have to eat to buy an iPhone, you don’t have to
тебе чтобы купить iPhone вот не кушать
spend money, to buy an iPhone
не тратить тебе чтобы купить iPhone
how many months do you need to work for two with an advance
сколько месяцев нужно работать два с
payment to me  in principle, if salary
авансом мне в принципе если зарплата
advance is added 20, let’s say how much
аванс добавить 20 давай так сколько
How much per month do you receive in total
Сколько за месяц ты получаешь в сумме
salary advance per month how much 50 60 Well
зарплата аванс за месяц сколько 50 60 Ну
yes  600 60 600 dollars That is,
да 600 60 600 долларов То есть тебе э
to get an iPhone you need to work for 2 months and
чтобы получить iPhone нужно 2 месяца
not eat anything to get an
работать не кушать ничего чтобы получить
iPhone Yes, a person in California
iPhone Да человек в Калифорнии iPhone
can buy an iPhone in about a month and still have
может купить за о месяц и у него ещё
a lot of money left, yes yes Well, look,
останется куча денег да да Ну вот смотри
if he gets it, he will work,
если он получает он будет работать
look  a teacher at a university in a
смотри преподаватель в университете в
store there or so on, yes, that is,
магазине там или так дальше да то есть
well, he gets, for example, 9,000
там ну он получает например 9.000
dollars Yes, he spent 1,200 on an iPhone,
долларов Да он потратил на iPhone 1.200
he still has how much
у него ещё остаётся Сколько
dollars a car is also according to All Americans
долларов машину также по Все американцы
they drive cars because they can
на автомобилях ездят потому что могут
afford to buy them, but for a Russian you
себе позволить купить а для россиянина
need to collect some kind of Lada Vesta for
нужно на какую-то Ладу весту собирать
like, damn, half your life, you know, and then
типа блин полжизни знаешь а потом ещё
like, half your life with it already. Well,
типа полжизни с ней вже Ну там а жильё у
their housing is very expensive, the rent is expensive,
них же очень дорогая аренда дорогой
look, look about Yes, mani the factory there
смотри смотри насчёт Да мани там заводу
they pay stop stop I’ll say this about
они платят стоп стоп я скажу так про ээ
expensive housing for people in Moscow and St. Petersburg
дорогое жильё людям в Москве и в Питере
to open your mouth no no somehow comme il faut
открывать рот не не как-то не комильфо
the truth is it’s expensive  housing is always when there
правда вот дорогое жильё всегда когда
is population growth where people
идёт прирост населения там где люди
come to big cities, there is
приезжают в Большие города там идёт
a demand for housing and of course housing is
спрос на жильё и конечно там жильё
more expensive there. But when people from Russia say
дороже Но когда люди из России говорят
expensive housing, for some reason they compare
дорогое жильё они сравнивают почему-то
the Khrushchev apartment in Moscow and the murdered one for which
хрущёвку в Москве да убитую за которую
you pay as much as for a two-story
платишь столько сколько за двухэтажный
house with  territory in America, Americans
дом с территорией в Америке американцы
don’t live in Khrushchev-era apartment buildings. True, they
не живут в хрущёвках Правда они себе
rent for themselves, like houses there, and like
берут снимают типа там домики да типа
there are servants, like two-story ones, you see, they’re
там служака типа двухэтажные ты вишь вот
all American  films are true Look,
все американские фильмы правда Посмотри
they still
они все же так
live like this, the majority of Americans live here, but
живут большинство американцев да живёт
here they live with us, look at how it was in the Soviet Union,
вот у нихто у нас смотри в совке как
but in Ukraine, I also
было да вот у меня в Украине тоже
set up these Khrushchev-era Khrushchev-era apartments,
настроить вот этих хрущёвок хрущёвок
but in America it’s completely different, that
правда в Америке совсем по-другому то
is, in America, if you look at an
есть в Америке если смотри такая
apartment like this  here, yes, Khrushchev
квартирка как у нас да хрущёвка
is considered to be some kind of fire in the
считается это вообще какой-то огонь в
Soviet Union, they built these
Советском Союзе строили вот эти
chicken coops Yes, to save space because so that
курятники Да из экономии места потому
people could live in cheap crypts like a
что чтобы дёшево склепа люди жили как а
in America it’s not like that, well, look at the
в Америке не так ну ты ну посмотри
films. How ordinary people live, it’s not
фильмы Как живут обычные люди это же не
like there. Well, for example,
то что там Ну например
sometimes they rent apartments, here’s the film 1
квартиры иногда же снимают вот фильм 1
+1, again they show these
+1 там опять же показаны вот эти
apartments in five-story
квартиры в пятиэтажных
buildings, just compare them Compare them with
домах вот просто Сравни Сравни их с
the key Compare simple apartments  among
ключёвка Сравни простые квартиры у
ordinary Americans there and among ordinary
простых американцев там и у простых
Russians Well, this is heaven and earth yes Well yes yes
россиян Ну это небо и земля да Ну да да
they may have it worse Yes, so in short it
у них может и хуже Да так короче
turns out that Vika got a point from us
получается балл получила у нас Вика
and no one got it from you not Vika
и а не никто не получил у вас не Вика
Vika got Vika Yes six yes and  now the
Вика получил Вика Да шесть да и сейчас
last tour yes 64 64 we have the last
последний тур да 64 64 у нас последний
tour the last tour the last tour What do you
тур последний тур последний тур Как вы
think
считаете
[music]
[музыка]
where in which country is there more democracy in
где в какой стране больше демократии в
Russia or in the
России или в
USA in the
США в
USA Vic
США Вик
a Can you go into more detail Where is the level of
а Можно поподробнее Где выше уровень
democracy higher, that’s the question, I don’t
демократии вот вопрос так я его не
go into detail about it Where is more  Freedom, word
детализирует Где больше Свободы слово
of everything, freedom in general in the USA, in principle, but not
всего вообще свобод США в принципе да не
in Russia, no. So you both get a
в России нет Так вы оба получаете по
point and we have a score of 75. The dumbest question
баллу и у нас счёт 75 самый тупой вопрос
seems to me with this ST Vita
мне кажется с этим СТ Виты
thought about it, I didn’t think about it, I’m just already
задумалась я не задумалась Я просто уже
all I  I worked so many shifts that we
вс Я отработала столько смен что мы
drank so much beer by the way Well, look at the
Столько пива выпили к слову Ну смотри по
rules Yes, we played until seven Vika
правилам Да мы играли до семи Вика
won but I’ll be honest You both
победила но я скажу честно Вы обе хорошо
played well and uh just
играли да э просто
uh Nastya lost points on a couple of questions
ээ Настя на пару вопросах потеряла баллы
But in general, well done I thought that
А так вообще молодец прошла Я думал что
you would have  worse results And you are great
у вас будет хуже результаты А вы молодцы
You surprised me And you thought that we were
Вы меня удивили А вы думали что что мы
bad We are from the province m I just remember the
плохие Мы из провинции м я просто помню
beginning of our conversation when you
начало нашего разговора когда вы
turned on
включили
what and waved there
что и помахали там
And this Sorry please, I somehow
А это Извините пожалуйста я как-то
know I thought knew with  We’re communicating
знаете подумал знали с общаемся Мы же
We’re joking We’re joking We didn’t know who we were
шутим мы же шутим мы не знали с кем
communicating with What’s the joke, for example, that you’re
общаемся А в чём шутка например что вы
coming out and seeing a man from Ukraine
выходите э видите человека из Украины
who’s being bombed by your country Nope, we’re not right away
который ваша страна бомбит нене не мы мы
somi We’re not at all We didn’t notice right away
не сразу соми мы совсем Мы не сразу
Sorry, I understand Pony doesn’t mean that at all
заметили Извините понял Поня совсем так
meanings where the person is from
не имеет значения откуда человек
Listen, here’s an example We
Слушайте а вот вот например Мы нормально
talk normally Maybe you want to ask the
разговариваем Может вам хочется задать
Ukrainians some questions to
украинцам какие-то вопросы чтобы что-то
ask us something Yes, ask
у нас спросить Да вот спросите у
me I don’t know, just The only thing I
меня не знаю просто Единственное чего я
don’t understand is why send newsletters
не понимаю это зачем присылать рассылки
Yes, basically it’s like from
ской Да вот в основном такое как бы от
Okay there Telegram channels I
Ладно там Telegram каналах Это я всё
see everything, they just throw people’s accounts
вижу просто аккаунты людей
off and say look what you
скидывают говорят смотрите что вы
did, it’s your
натворили
fault and what did I do?
виноваты а я что делала
People understand everything super question So
ять Люде всё супер вопрос понял Значит
look Why do people from Ukraine
смотри Почему люди из Украины Да
send Yes to their relatives and not
присылают своим родственникам и не
only  Yes, these are such unpleasant
только Да вот такие неприятные
photographs because the majority of
фотографии потому что большинство
Russians Yes, when
россиян Да вот когда началось
the full-scale invasion even began,
полномасштабное даже вторжение
most Russians pretended that, well,
большинство россиян делало вид что ну
this does not concern me, we live, we do not
меня это не касается мы живём мы не
bomb, Yes, we are like  somewhere there everything is in And
бомбим Да мы типа где-то там все во А
missiles and drones fly here when a
сюда прилетают ракеты дроны когда
person sees that his relatives have died,
человек да видит что у него погибли
that his friends have died,
родственники что у него погибли знакомые
that a rocket has arrived Here are the girls there,
что прилетела ракета Вот девочки там
the vine has torn off like a lot of people She
виница оторвала типа на многи Она
died in the children's hospital of this Ahmadi
погибла в детскую эту больницу Ахмади
children flew in and died Yes people see and
прилетела погибли дети Да люди видят и
they want you to see what
они хотят чтобы вы увидели что делает
your country is doing so that you can feel it,
ваша страна чтобы вы почувствовали это
we feel it, yes it’s unpleasant for us, just like that,
мы чувствуем да нам неприятно вот так
look what you have. Millions of people keep
вот смотри что у вас Миллионы людей все
saying, It’s not us, it’s not us, but
говорят Это ж не мы это же не мы но
nothing  they don’t and we want you to
ничего не делают и мы хотим Да чтобы вы
understand that this also concerns you
поняли что это вас тоже касается и
now, when the adult generation began to fly across the
сейчас когда начало прилетать по
territory,
территории взрослому поколения в
mainly from now when more began to fly in.
основном с сейчас когда начало прилетать
What are we going to change, what now, wait,
ещё А что мы поменяем что сейчас подожди
look, I’ll tell you first what it’s for.
смотри я тебе сначала скажу для чего Вот
This is also now  as they began to fly
это де Также сейчас как начало прилетать
across the territory of the Russian Federation,
по территории Российской Федерации
people’s attitudes began to change dramatically;
начало резко меняться у людей отношения
everyone somehow began to become more against the war.
все уже как-то начали против войны
Yes, in the Belgorod region, in the
больше ставать Да в Белгородской ой в
Kursk region, where
Курской области там где
resettlement was done with Putin’s demand to
отселить сделали с требованием Путина
stop the war, yes yes  in the Korenevsky
остановить войну да да в коренёвский
district Yes, they wrote it down there in general, yes,
район Да там записали это вообще да то
that is, they lived for 2 years, they didn’t care. Yes,
есть они жили 2 года им было плевать Да
from the territory of their Kursk region they are
что с территории ихней Курской области
bombing Ukraine, shelling them, and
бомбят Украину обстреливают заходят Да
here, when it touched them, they were also out of
тут когда коснулось их они были тоже вне
politics, nothing depended on them, they
политики от них ничего не зависело они
said What will we do  we’ll go to a
говорили А что мы сделаем мы выйдем на
rally, we’ll be like, it’s okay, but then when to
митинг нас типа ничего а тут когда их
resettle them, it’s war, they’re already
отселить война они уже
doing mine, stop the war because I
делать мин станови войну потому что
’ll touch them, and that’s why the Ukrainians
коснусь их и вот поэтому украинцы
think that the war should affect
считают Да что война должна коснуться
the majority of the population of the Russian
большинства населения Российской
Federation then  the Kursk region will begin to turn on, they
Федерации тогда начнёт включаться
understand, the Kursk region is
Курская область поняли Курская область
already against the war, it is already against the war,
уже против войны она уже против войны
it doesn’t want to attack Ukraine, so
она не хохочет нападать на Украину так
all the adequate people are against the war,
все адекватные Люди против войны
right Yes, but they are all silent from the Kursk
правильно Да но они все молчат акур
region
область
and Belgorod too, and Belgorod too,
ми и Белгород тоже да и Белгород потому
because Belgorod felt Kursk even earlier than
что Белгород ещё раньше Курска ощутил но
Kursk  uh, it’s good that Ukraine has entered Kursk
Курск э в Курск хорошо Украина зашла да
and that’s all Belgorod anyway, it’s all the same from
и всё Белгород так всё равно от мнения
people’s opinions. Nothing will change, the government
людей Ничего не поменяется правительство
decides, look, look when when everyone
решает смотри смотри когда когда каждый
sits in the kitchen and says what’s their opinion  will
сидит на кухне и говорит что от мнение
not change Nothing will change, but
не поменяется Ничего не поменяется но
when people are brought to the point of tension they go out to
когда люди доведён до накала выходят в
Sudzha in Belgorod And so on Yes, it’s possible
Судже в Белгороде И так дальше Да можно
if they go out somewhere in one they are imprisoned and
если выходят где-то в одно их сажают и
look at this in Korenevsky there is
вот смотри в это в коренёвский
already popular discontent Yes, you can’t
уже народное недовольство Да уже не
do it anymore And until it happens This is  such
сделаешь И пока не будет Вот это такое
That in every town they will start to
Что в каждом городке начнут Вот это
riot And then of course they will say
бунтовать А тогда конечно будут говорить
that A type of don’t care and the authorities really look
что А типа пофиг а власть очень смотри
In the authorities, too, people worry about their own
Во власти тоже люди за свою переживают
truth Clearly, Putin is there somewhere in
правда Ясно Там Путину там где-то в
The Kremlin, if something flies away somewhere by helicopter,
Кремле если что вертолётом где-то улетит
and the governor is the mayor And so on,
да а губернатор мэр И так дальше не
that’s not why it’s very All these, for example,
поэтому очень Всё эти вот например от
nothing depends on people Yes, they seem to say,
людей ничего не зависит Да вроде говорят
but because of the riots in the Kursk region, they
но из-за бунтов в Курской области да
replaced the head of the Sudzhansky district, the head of the
сменили главу суджанского района главу
Korenevsky district somehow  changed
коренёвский района уже как-то поменяли
Yeah, that is, although it seemed Yes, for all the
Угу то есть хотя казалось Да всеми
years people have been saying nothing
годами люди говорили ничего ничего не
solves anything. And when Sorry, it got hot, they
решают А когда Извини припекло они
just had no way out, they began, in short, to hold
просто уже Выхода нет они начали короче
rallies and seethe and swear at the
и митинговать и кипише ть и ругаться на
authorities and  everything and no one zak not that’s all
власть и всё и никто зак не вот и всё
That’s the logic I have, well, it cost
Вот такая логика у меня ну это стоило
the lives of
жизни
people, many lives And our
людей чх гих жизней А наших мальчиков
young boys are sent simply without preparation,
молодых отправляют просто без подготовки
which also cost their
тоже что стоило
lives Well, you say that yes they attacked
жизни Ну вот вы говорите что да напали
Kursk That’s all yes Ukraine for and
на Курск Вот это всё да Украина заа и
only  after that people realized yes What is it
только после этого люди осознали да Что
like to show something negative towards the authorities
такое проявлять как бы негатив к власти
What is it like to speak out against the authorities it
Что такое выступать против власти это
cost so many lives in general the lives of
стоило стольких жизни вообще жизни
some people just people what
кого людей просто народа каких
Ukrainian Russians and it doesn’t matter in general
украинских русских а неважно вообще вот
what they attacked and only after that don’t
то что напали да и только после этого не
look no no  now everyone is attacked,
смотри не не напали теперь всех
not Ukraine attacked the Kursk
надо не Украина напала на курскую
region, but Russia attacked Ukraine,
область а Россия напала на Украину в том
including from the territory of the Kursk region, and
числе из территории Курской области а
Ukraine is giving stars to Russian
Украина даёт звездюлей российским
troops, including in the territory of the
войскам в том числе и на территории
Kursk region, and yes, these people
Курской области и да да будут эти люди
will suffer until the troops of the Russian
будут страдать пока ээ войска Российской
Federation  will leave Ukraine and will not
Федерации не уйдут из Украины и не
stop shelling Ukrainian territory
прекратят обстрелы украинской территории
and also when, for example, drones fly from Ukraine
и также когда например с Украины летят
Yes they bomb Belgorod they bomb Lipetsk
дроны Да бомбят Белгород бомбят Липецк
where it flies Yes there is Kazan
куда долетает Да там Казань
Krasnodar Territory Yes, someone flew into the
Краснодарский край Да кому-то прилетел в
oil base and flew in to Saratov, he
нефти базу прилетела А вон в Саратове
flew nearby out of spite Yes, he flew to Saratov
летел тут рядом на зла Да в Саратов
to a military airfield Yes, this drone is
летел на аэродром военный Да этот Дрон
Ukrainian and ended up in a thirty-seven-
украинский и попал в тридцати семи
story building Yes, because she is healthy, so he
этажку Да потому что она здоровая вот он
ended up in my area for  outside my window, outside
попал это в моём районе за окном моим за
my window, I’m not talking in Saratov In
моим окном не я говорю в Саратове В
Saratov And you, too, somewhere here Well,
Саратове А у вас тоже где-то вот Ну у
we also have a thirty-
нас тоже есть тридцати
seven-story building and I see, I’ll honestly say
семиэтажка и я смотрю вот я честно скажу
I don’t  I’m sorry, I don’t feel sorry for the people in the
Мне не жалко мне не жалко людей в
Russian Federation, because they attacked
Российской Федерации пото что они напали
us very much, we can’t stop the war. But I feel sorry, that’s right, but I don’t feel sorry because the Russian Federation came to kill us, you can stop the war, you can just, the
нас убить остановить войну можно просто
Russian Federation withdraws its troops
Российская Федерация выводит войска свои
all in one day and no  wars and we can’t
всё один день и нет войны а мы не можем
stop the war, the Russian Federation
остановить войну Российская Федерация
can do that, that’s all. Therefore, in order for
может вот и всё Поэтому Чтобы перестали
boys to stop dying, in order for
погибать мальчики Чтобы перестали
drones to stop flying into the neighboring area,
прилетать в соседний район беспилотники
Russia needs to withdraw
нужно чтобы Россия отвела
Well, Zelensky will just give up, yes I
Ну а Зеленский просто руки опустит да В
mean he will, Well  so if you look, if
смысле опустит Ну так если смотри если
Russia leaves Ukraine and
Россия вот Россия выйдет из Украины и
stands on its borders, we won’t
встанет на своих границах всё Мы же не
go there, but what if the USA is already behind
полезем туда а что это уже США как бы за
you, as
вами уже как
if Kursk is already under you, so look,
бы уже Курск всё под вами так смотри так
I’ll exchange Kursk, like for Ukraine
Курск обменяю типа наза что Украина
leaving Kursk  and Russia is leaving the
выходит из Курска а Россия выходит из
Donetsk Lugansk region and Crimea is
Донецкой Луганской области и Крыма
being given away as an exchange, that’s all there, look at
отдают обменка вот и всё есть тут смотри
Ukraine,
Украине
here are Ukraine’s clear goals Yes, the return of its
вот цели Украины чёткие Да возврат своей
territory is all Ukraine doesn’t need other
территории всё Украине не нужны другие
territories, why would we never  they
территории зачем мы никогда не
were trying to take over Why do we need those
претендовали забрать Зачем нам те
territories? We want to develop our own. We
территории мы своей хотим развиваться Мы
want to, but Russia is a huge country, it
хотим вот а России огромная страна она
can’t build roads properly, it
дороги не может построить нормально не
can’t provide housing for people. Yes, it’s
может обустроить людям жильё Да
affordable. And it wants to capture more new
доступная А хочет захватывать ещ новых
people, new territories, you know, the world
людей новые территории понимаешь мир
thinks differently; the world already was once Yes.
мыслит по-другому мир уже когда-то Да
in ancient times, history was what it was.
вот в древности история была в чём было
Well, why did people capture each
Ну почему люди захватывали Да друг
other? For example, they live with nothing to
друга Вот например они живут нечего
eat; they got together;
жрать они взяли собрались пошли
took away food
табло забрало еду
Yes, people didn’t have this kind of
Да у людей не было как бы этого
accumulation of food, yes, that is, they
накопление еды да то есть они вот что
caught what they ate, then, for example,
поймали то сожрали потом например
agriculture appeared. People were already
появилась сельское хозяйство Люди уже
sowing and collecting there. They could
там сеяли собирали Они могли делать
stock up for the winter, yes, that is, the
запасы на зиму да то есть начали
state began to develop there. There are cities
развиваться там государство Там города
because it was possible.  feed more
потому что можно было прокормить больше
people and then Well, there were still wars
людей да потом Ну всё равно были войны
Yes, because there were few resources, it was necessary to
Да потому что ресурсов мало нужно было
capture people there Because these people
там захватить людей Потому что эти люди
made you more grain, they mined
тебе делали больше зерна добывали там
some kind of stone there And so on, then inventions began to appear in
какого-то камня И так дальше потом в
countries that developed normally
странах которые нормально развивались
Yes, humanity  There are
изобретения Да человечество изоб там
some machines there Yes, there are steamships
машины какие-то Да изоб там пароходы
and steam locomotives Yes, he invented electricity And
паровозы Да изобрел электричество Да и
now it doesn’t make sense to
сейчас сейчас не имеет смысла
capture 100 workers who will
захватывать 100 робов который будут на
manually collect this wheat in the field, now
поле вручную собирать это пшеницу сейчас
one combine will collect in a day as much as
один комбайн соберёт за день столько
100 people can’t collect in a week,
сколько 100 человек не собира за неделю
you know, that is, to feed  these 100
понимаешь то есть прокормить этих 100
robes are more expensive than refueling one combine harvester
робов дороже чем заправить один комбайн
and it will do it more and better, so
и он сделает это больше и лучше поэтому
the world is becoming rich not because they
мир стаёт богатым не из-за того что он
capture territories or people, but  because of
захватывают территории или людей а из-за
technology. For example, take Switzerland. A
технологий Вот например возьми Швейцария
small country is generally small; it is
Маленькая страна вообще маленькая она
smaller than some Orel region of
меньше там какой-то Орловской области
yours or Voronezh region, where it is smaller than the
вашей или там Воронежской откуда меньше
Voronezh region. And life is much
Воронежской области А жит насколько
richer than all of Russia; for
богаче всей России поче
example, Estonia is generally small; there are
например Эстония вообще маленькая там
half a million people there, and even less people live
пол млн населения а живёт ещё меньше
now. No.  not oil and gas diamonds
сейчас Да нет не нефти и газа алмазов
salaries are higher than in Russia why so
зарплаты выше чем в России почему так
Who ruined everything there what kind of people
Кто у нас там развалил всё какие люди У
We were in power in
нас у власти были в
Vincha what Putin
винчу какие Путин
how much Yeltsin what did he do there what
сколько Ельцин что он там натворил какой
is look  Putin since ninety-nine,
есть смотри Путин с девяносто девятого
you were born under Putin,
года вы походу родились уже при Путине
yes
да
Well, look, Putin became
со да то смотри Путин в де дем стал
president a year later, you were born, yes,
президентом через лет ше вы родились да
that is, it turns out neither Yeltsin nor Gorbach
то есть получается ни Ельцин ни Горбач
You have been conscious all your life, yes, you have already grown up
Вы всю жизнь сознательную да вы выросли
Yes, that’s it And Putin is up to  still rules during
уже Да всё А Путин до сих пор правит за
this time it was possible to build I don’t know
это время можно было построить не знаю
what but to reform everything and so on
что да реформировать всё и так дальше
who is to blame neither Yeltsin nor Gorbachev nor
кто виноват ни Ельцин ни Горбачёв ни там
Niko so rich countries become
Нико так вот богатые страны стают
rich from
богатыми из
not because they are there, Japan
не из-за того что они там вот Япония
Take Japan, an island on which there are
Возьмите Япония остров на котором
very few resources as such, it
ресурсов как таковых очень мало она
buys oil there, buys iron, they
покупает там нефть покупает железо по ей
bring it and they create cars,
привозят и они создают автомобили
create robots, create a lot of everything, it’s
создают роботов создают куча всего
true. It’s clear,
правда Понятно
therefore, to Ukraine, what am I driving at? Yes,
поэтому Украине К чему я веду Да
seize the territory of Russia  Absolutely
захватывать территорию России абсолютно
not necessary, but a resource What resource
не нужно а ресурс Какие ресур
can you buy, what will we take from you,
можно купить что что мы захватим у вас
you are selling and so the resource you were selling
вы продаёте и так ресурс вы продавали
Why look, Why should Germany take over
Зачем смотри Зачем Германии захватывать
Russia if you can just buy GAZ and not
Россию если можно просто купить ГАЗ и не
worry about it, but take over and pay pensions to
париться а захвати плати пенсии этим
all these people  like make roads for them and
всем людям типа устраивай им дороги и
so on That's
так дальше Вот и
all, Britain was once the
всё вот Британия была когда-то
British Empire India was part of the
британская Империя Индия была частью
British Empire Yes Pakistan was there and a
Британской Империи Да Пакистан был там
bunch of other countries But nothing England
ещё куча всяких стран Да ничего Англия
Britain Empire once Well, she threw herself off, why does
Британия импери раз Ну скинула себя эти
she need India with this billion
зачем ей Индия с этим миллиардом
population So what  you need can buy from them
населения Да что нужно могут у них
and so that’s all Therefore,
купить так вот и всё Поэтому а к
unfortunately, both the Russian authorities and the majority of the
сожалению и власти России и большинство
population of the Russian Federation think in
населения Российской Федерации мыслит
these old categories, we need to
вот этими старыми категориями нам надо
seize the territory people There and so
территорию захватить люди Там и так
on Yes Question Yes when
дальше Да Вопрос Да когда вот мне
many of yours tell me
говорят Многие ваши
The Russians have captured Mariupol, we
россияне вот захватили Мариуполь мы там
built some houses for them there, I
для них построили э каких-то дома я
say this. What was the problem with just
говорю так А в чём была проблема просто
building and saying, well, come to us?
построить и сказать ну приезжайте к нам
Yes, what’s the problem with building for you,
Да в чём проблема построить для вас вот
you are young girls, and in order to
вы молодые девушки да вам чтобы
earn money for an apartment you need to
заработать себе на квартиру нужно на
work In short, there are many decades there
работе Короче там сколько десятков лет
True Well, yes Why does Russia have Gas
Правда Ну это да Почему Россия имее Газ
Oil diamonds Yes, it can buy a yacht for the
Нефть алмазы Да может купить яхту для
authorities, but it can’t make it so that
власти а не может сделать так чтобы
young girls don’t have to
молодые девушки да могли ээ не
worry about the future
переживать о будущем
And understand that they are there, why
А понимать что они там за че там 5 лет
can they have an apartment there for 5 years  yat, or when you
могут там квартиру вять или когда вот вы
said that in America prices in America are
говорили что в Америке цены в Америке
mortgages, now you have the National Bank making
ипотека вот у вас сейчас Нацбанк сделал
loans In short, you have something like 20 percent
кредиты Короче у вас что-то там 20 с
23% That is, it’s impossible to get a loan from you
чем-то Процев 23% То есть у вас кредит
for an apartment, it’s true, it’s
взять невозможно на квартиру правда Это
just fire for
просто огонь
you  You will have to pay for 50 years and
будет вам 50 лет придётся выплачивать и
then you will die and not pay, but in America
то умрёте и не выплатить да а в Америке
there is a 2% 3%
там 2% 3%
mortgage, that’s all, yes, America
ипотека вот и всё то есть да в Америке
also has its problems because
тоже есть свои проблемы потому что
why do people always want to live better
почему люди люди хотят жить всегда лучше
than they
чем они
live  America lives better than Russia, but
живут Америка живёт круче чем Россия но
she doesn’t look at Russia. She looks at how
она не смотрит на Россию Она смотрит как
she wants to live, that’s all, how much do you,
она хохочет жить вот и всё сколько вы
for example, work a
вот например работаете в
day a day, and
день в день да
how many hours? Yes, I work
сколько часов
10 to 11.
Да я по 10 по 11
And in Europe, If you worked
работаю А в Европе Если бы вы работали
11 hours. Yes, employer  would be fined
11 часов Да работодателя оштрафовали бы
yes Yes I’m not the one asking for so many
да Да не я сама прошу иногда столько
hours sometimes Why Because you need
часов Почему Потому что тебе нужны
money Yes yes because look
деньги Да да потому что смотри потому
because I understand Because some people
что я понимаю Потому что некоторые идут
take two or three jobs Yes in order to survive in order
на две-три работы Да чтобы выжить
to survive Yes and you’re great you
чтобы выжить Да и ты молодец ты
you’re spinning Yes, somehow you need to, but the question is
крутишься Да как-то нужно но вопрос
why are you in a country where there is oil,
почему ты в стране в которой есть нефть
gas, diamonds, you have to come for 12 hours and then
газ алмазы должна 12 часов потом
come and fall off your feet at home? Yes, you have
приходить никакая падать с ног дома Да у
no personal life because of this, and
тебя нет ни личной жизни из-за этого да
you can’t study there, nor any development
ни какого-то развития ты не можешь там
and because you have to
поучиться и потому что ты должна
survive, that’s the way the authorities
выживать вот власти так и
have done it, but someone, in short,
делано у кото кто-то короче на нефтяной
is sitting on an oil needle, of course not everyone has No, let’s
игле сидит конечно не у всех Нет давайте
take into account the fact that Vika has no
учтём тот факт что у Вики нет
education Yes, no secondary education Ana
образования Да ни среднего никакого Ана
No, well, like a secondary school is high school  On
Не ну как среднего средняя школа это
average, he earns three to four times
раз зарабатывать раза в три в четыре
more, and in order to buy an iPhone, he doesn’t
больше и ему уже чтобы купить iPhone не
have to think that
надо думать что
he’ll have to work for 2 months and eat nothing, he’ll
ой 2 месяца работать и ничего не есть он
also go and buy a
также пойдёт себе и купит и образование
free education, unlike the USA. Yes,
бесплатное в отличие от США Да
education, medicine, everything’s
образование медицина всё
free. I wanted to, I didn’t
бесплатно захотел поступил не
want to.  the question is education is free then it’s
захотел вопрос образование бесплатно то
free Everything like why then people from
бесплатно Всё как почему тогда люди из
Russia en masse leave to live in the USA but
России массово уезжают в США жить а из
don’t leave the USA for Russia anyway I
США в Россию не уезжают ть то вс-таки
don’t know where it’s better I don’t have any friends who
лучше не знаю у меня нет знакомых
moved to the USA Well you know people
которые в США переехал Ну ты знаешь люди
from Russia are moving to the USA
с России переезжают в США
Truth  and then they come back, well, only a few
правда и возвращаются потом ну единицы
who are even storytellers Well look Yes The point is
кто вообще сказочник Ну смотри Да Суть в
that we can compare Yes that people
том что мы можем сравнить Да что люди
who live in Russia in the richest
которые живут в России в богатейшей
country in terms of resources Yes in terms of opportunities they
стране по ресурсам Да по возможностям
live poorer than people in European countries in
живут беднее чем люди в странах Европы в
small countries Yes who told you this
маленьких странах Да кто вам это сказал
Nuno this  it’s very easy to even look at
нуно это очень просто даже посмотреть
the level of the average salary median
уровень средней зарплаты медианной
salary minimum salary So I already
зарплаты минимальная зарплаты Так я уже
said that in Russia you can
говорила о том что в России Ты можешь
receive 300-400,000 a month but spend
получать 300-400 000 в месяц но тратить
less than you in the USA you will receive the same amount
меньше чем ты в США получишь столько же
but spend  twice as much just
но потратишь в два раза больше просто
to live on food for
чтобы жить на продукты на
everything 300-400,000 a month Yes in Russia it’s
всё 300-400 000 в месяц Да в России это
34,000 dollars
34.000 долларов
Who in Russia gets 34 dollars
Кто в России получает 34 долларов
300-400 a
300-400 ся в
month My dad is what he
месяц Мой папа кем он
works for, he graduated from a flight school and
работает он отучился в лётном училище и
went to work as a pilot pilot  Yes,
пошёл работать лётчиком лётчик Да
pilots, pilots, captains of ships, Yes,
лётчики лётчики капитаны кораблей Да
they get Super, these are only
получают Супер это
a few. Why are there only people in all of Russia,
единицы Почему едиль чиков на всю Росси
IT specialists,
айтишники
education, doctors, everyone?  get it Well
образование медики все получают Хорошо
Whoever wants it gets it, and the rest
Кто хочет тот получает а остальные
just That is, it turns out the rest
просто То есть получается остальные
just don’t want to get it
просто не хотят получать
Well, you
Да
don’t need
ну не нужно
education, I understand correctly that I
образование я правильно понимаю что я
understand correctly that you and Vika don’t
правильно понимаю что ты с Викой не
want to receive 3,000 dollars since you don’t
хотите получать 3.000 долларов раз не
get it Yes, in the sense of
получаете Да в смысле
Nuri, I’m learning from me I have  plans I'm a
Нури Я учусь у меня есть планы Я
student my
студентка
parents help me in the World Cup problem I'm not
родители мне помогают в ЧМ проблема Я не
complaining I don't want to go to the States so
жалуюсь я не хочу в Штаты чтобы
what so wait my parents help you with something
что так подожди родители тебе чем
morally I'm helping me for my studies my
помогают морально мне помогаю за учёбу
parents don't pay for my studies Who pays for my
платят родители не платят Кто платит за
studies I'm studying on a budget
учёбу Я на бюджете учусь
now as  I entered higher
сейчас как поступила
education and
над вз и
training at
по бы в
school before the
школе перед
exam. Of course, this is related to the issue of
эгэ Конечно вот это к вопросу о
free
бесплатном
education, that is, after all, it is paid,
образовании то есть всё-таки оно платное
yes. In order to enroll somewhere, you have to
да Для того чтобы куда-то поступить
hire tutors. And so
приходится и нанимать репетиторов И так
on, after all, there is truth. Well,
дальше всё-таки есть правда Ну потому
because I don’t  prodigy, I wasn’t an excellent student, they’re
что я не вундеркинд я не была отличницей
not prodigies. You see, for some reason, you
все не вундеркинды Вот видишь почему-то
have to rehearse in order to get in,
Да чтобы поступить приходится
and Vika’s parents didn’t
репетировать а у Вики у родителей не
have money for tutors, she didn’t go, it’s
было денег на репетиторов она не пошла
true,
правда
Vic, and I didn’t get in there  the situation is complicated
Вик а я не поступила там ситуацию сложно
Well, it’s complicated Yes, well, agree that Vika Yes, for
Ну сложно Да ну согласись что Вика Да
example, Nastya doesn’t have one, look, as I
вот например у Насти нет смотри я так
understand it, Nastya’s parent is Dad’s a pilot
понимаю у Насти родитель Это папа лётчик
Yes, he can allocate, for example, some
Да он может выделить например какие-то
money for tutors Yes, you
деньги на репетиторов Да ты с более
were from a poorer family somewhere yes That is, you  I
бедной семьи где-то была да То есть ты
couldn’t your parents couldn’t
не могла твои родители не могли тебе
give you tutors, so it
дать репетиторов так
turns out, yes, you understand that it’s not in
получается да вы понимаете что не в
tutors
репетиторах
where the situation is different. It’s
де там другая ситуация
just my own fault that
Я просто сама виновата что
the year, you know, I have classmates
год понимаете У меня есть одноклассники
who studied very well and without
которые очень хорошо учились и без
tutors entered the  the best universities in
репетиторов поступили в лучшие ВУЗы
the country and they will earn well And
страны и будут они зарабатывать хорошо И
live well super super Look, I’m taking it
жить хорошо супер супер Смотри я беру
now yes the median salary in Russia
сейчас да медианная зарплата в России
Look at the focus median
Вот смотри фокус медианная
salary in Russia
зарплата в России
What is the median salary if
Что такое медианная зарплата это если
you take all the people and take them in half Yes, that’s
взять всех людей и взять пополам Да вот
how much those who are exactly
сколько получают те которые вот ровно
in the middle get  Yes, the median salary in
посередине Да так медианная зарплата в
Russia is now 82,000 rubles 82,000 rubles, that
России сейчас 82.000 руб 82000 руб то
is, half of the people in Russia receive
есть половина людей в России получает
less than 82,000 rubles per month, that is, 820
меньше чем 82000 руб в месяц то есть 820
dollars That is,
долларов То есть
look, half the population of the Russian
Смотри половина населения Российской
Federation
Федерации
People receive less than 820
Люде получает меньше 820
dollars Yes, some of the pilots receive
долларов Да кто-то из лётчиков получает
more, some of the captain of the ship receives, but
больше кто-то Капитан судна получает но
70 million people live on less than 800 And
70 млн людей живут на меньше чем 800 А
you know My mother also received 20,000
вы знаете Моя мама тоже получала 20.000
rubles 20,000 rubles and then you know
руб 20.000 руб а потом знаете как-то
somehow I decided that I wanted to
вот решила что хочет побольше
earn more and started earning
зарабатывать и начала зарабатывать
more How she
побольше Как она
moved moved Where she settled in
переехала переехала Куда обустроила в
another city what she started
другом городе чем начала
doing as a teacher she is all  life
заниматься она учитель она всю жизнь
works as a simple primary
работает простым учителем начальной
school teacher only in Voronezh she earned
школы только в Воронеже она зарабатывала
30,000 and in Moscow she earns
30.000 а в Москве она зарабатывает
100,000 super Well, in Moscow it’s more expensive for an
100.000 супер Ну и в Москве дороже на
apartment, but that’s true Yes, of course it’s
квартиру на это правда ж Да конечно это
better, and better than in Voronezh she gets
лучше да чем в Воронеже лучше получает
100,000 I agree Yes, that’s what Voronezh is 30
100.000 согласен Да вот чем Воронеже 30
yes but in  as a result, how much does he have
да но в результате сколько у него в
left in Moscow if that’s what you thought?
Москве остаётся если ты так считал
Daro, I do
Воронеже стоко же вот я говорю Даро я
n’t even Tell me even 100,000 for
даже не Вот скажи даже 100000 для
Moscow so much in Moscow renting
Москвы сль сколько в Москве аренда
an apartment for a very short time 50,000 Yes
квартиры очень короткое время 50.000 Да
50,000 that is, that is, look,
50.000 это то есть то есть смотри
one-room apartment Yes, yes, that is, for mom to
однушка Да да да то есть маме чтобы
rent a one-room apartment with you, it’s already necessary to
снять однушку с тобой это надо уже пол
shell out half of your salary Well, it depends where  another
зарплаты выложить Ну это смотря где ещё
50,000 Well, in short, you don’t have to count further.
50.000 Ну короче Дальше можно не считать
I understand that this is hard, that is, your
Я понимаю что это тяжело то есть твоя
mother is not a millionaire because of this, well then  there is the
мама не миллионер из-за этого ну то есть
fact that it escaped from Voronezh, it’s
то что она вырвалась из Воронежа это
real, it’s super, yes, because Voronezh
реально это супер да потому что Воронеж
Well, 30,000 is the world, there is
Ну 30.000 это мира это
no Bazaar, but look at what, Yes, it’s a
Базару нет Вот но смотри к чему Да город
million-plus city. And in general, what am I leading to?
миллионник Да вообще к чему я веду Да
Yes, the countries of the country have not lived in
что страны страны уже давно не живут в
the paradigm for a long time in order to be  the rich
парадигме для того чтобы быть богатым
need to capture another square
нужно захватить ещё какой-то квадратный
kilometer, what else is needed, for example, to
километр что нужно ещё например
capture 10 people, you know
захватить 10 человек каких-то знаешь там
how
как
slaves technology makes people rich
рабов технологии делают людей богатыми
tags countries rich If we watch the
теги страны богатыми Если мы смотрим те
same America yes  And so on, we
же самые Америка да И так дальше мы
post-Soviet countries are
постсоветские страны отстаём
technologically lagging behind America just like
технологически от Америки просто как
heaven and earth there, new generation video cards are
небо и земля там видеокарты нового
developing processors in short,
поколения короче разрабатывают
developing And here we are lagging
процессоры разрабатывают А у нас что мы
behind When, for example,
совок совок отставал Когда например
look, I was born in 81 I was born in the
смотри я 81 года рождения Я родился в
Soviet Union back when
Советском Союзе ещё когда
it was in the Apple Corporation  already in the late
в этом в корпорация Apple уже в конце
seventies and early
семидесятых начала
eighties it produced a personal
восьмидесятых выпускала персональный
computer in America and people already
компьютер в Америке и у людей дома уже
had a computer at home, and in the Soviet Union a
был компьютер да в Советском Союзе
computer - it was something like that, you know,
компьютер - это было что-то такое знаешь
somewhere in the institute there was such a cabinet
где-то в институте стоял такой шкаф
healthy and it was a
здоровый и это был
computer Well, of course, yes, this cannot be
компьютер Ну конечно да это нельзя
denied because
отрицать потому
Well, yes It was a thing
что Ну да Было дело
Yes, and they were afraid to drink Coca-Cola, they couldn’t
Да и кока-колу боялись пить нельзя было
bring jeans Well, and now now the
джинсы привозить Ну ну и сейчас сейчас
same same narratives that the
такая же такие же самые нарративы что
West is bad What, in short,
вот Запад плохой Что короче
they all went to hell  bath we are all here Who
там пошли они все в баню мы тут всё Кто
says so The West, well done, they are doing their
так говорит Запад молодцы делают своё
job And what business does the
дело А какое дело
West have,
Запада что
what are the claims against them What do you
какие претензии к ним А как ты Как вы
think NATO wants to take over Russia
считаете НАТО хочет захватить Россию
America wants to take over Russia yes Net it
Америка хочет захватить России да Нетто
should be Correct Because many
надо Правильно Потому что мне многие
Russians tell me America wants to take over
россияне говорят Америка хочет захватить
I say, well, how old are they, why wouldn’t she have captured Perm when the Soviet Union collapsed and Russia was weak? So, what other questions do you have for me as a Ukrainian? How is the situation in Kiev now? Well, I’m not in Kiev. in Khmelnitsky It’s about 300 km from Kyiv uh I’ll say this in Kiev I was last month uh in Kyiv and we have air raid warnings and in Kyiv there are  air raids, but in Kyiv it’s somehow because they are closer to the border Yes, and plus in Kyiv Kyiv is attacked more often Yes, for example, My city was rarely attacked, there were arrivals yes But mostly In my region there are attacks and Kyiv around Kyiv regularly, that’s when I was in Kyiv Yes, at night Yes, these Heads are shooting down, it’s very hard for those cities that Kharkov, for example, is close to the border Kharkov is bombing, just huge bombs are being dropped on residential areas It’s just terrible, yes they are killing people Russia is not  It’s
тревоги и в Киеве есть воздушные тревоги
even planned, but there are no
задумано даже вот ну а так нет
safe cities, no, yes, they just exist, for
безопасных городов нету да просто есть
example, if people live in Kharkov. Yes, it’s
например если люди живут в Харькове Да
very dangerous there because there are
там очень опасно потому что бывают
arrivals before they even have time to turn on the siren.
прилёты до того как успеют даже сирену
Yes, cities like my
включить Да города Такие как мой
Khmelnitsky. Yes, they are relatively
Хмельницкий Да они относительно
safe. Yes, because, for example, the
безопасны Да потому что например
frequency of arrivals.  Maybe there
периодичность прилётов Может быть там
once every six months Yes, we are far from the front and
раз в полгода Да мы далеко от фронта и
therefore until something flies or
поэтому пока что-то долетает либо
shoots down or there are higher priority targets there. Well, yes, it
сбивает либо есть там более приоритетные
also happened that for example, we
Ну тоже да было что вот например у нас
had a woman just arrive  she was driving in a car
был прилёт женщина просто ехала в машине
Yes, she was killed like that, so what
Да её убило вот
was it like? Yes, there was a
так так что тут было такое Да что был
very strong attack. Yes, the
очень сильный прилёт Да целому
windows of the whole microdistrict were knocked out by all the
микрорайону окна по выбивало все там
doors there, and so on, that is, and with the
двери и так дальше то есть а с
Internet Well, the Internet is the Internet, yes,
интернетом Ну Интернет есть Интернет да
well, look, it was when
ну было смотри было когда
the attacks were in the last year  in the fall there were strikes
удары в вром году осенью были да удары
for the first time when the strikes hit the substation
по первый раз когда удары по подстанции
Uh-huh the light immediately went out, uh, it immediately disappeared, it
Угу сразу вырубился свет ээ сразу пропал
turns out the Internet is literally because,
получается Интернет буквально потому что
well, the city is without electricity. Well, everyone immediately went out on the
ну город без света Ну все сразу вышли на
street there, like shops there, well, everyone
улице там типа магазинчики там ну все
walks and walks, in short  At first they thought like,
ходят гуляют короче Сначала думали типа
well, now in an hour or
как ну сейчас там часик
so, like the light will be fixed. Yes, well, the light was already given, partially then in the evening, and in some
э частично тогда вечером а на некоторых
areas they were given. It’s late there and it’s balancing,
районах дали Там поздно и балансировать
for example, there’s light for 2 hours, 4 hours
например там 2 часа есть свет 4 часа
there’s no light, 2 hours there’s 4 no yes, for example,
нету 2 часа есть 4 нету да например
so that under Mush there would be  and this lasted, there were
чтобы под Муш было и такое длилось были
these interruptions in the light, then everything
эти перебои со светом потом всё уже
got better, firstly. People already have reserves with
наладилось во-первых Люди уже запаса с
generators, for example, if the lights
генераторами например свет если
were turned off, they were already turned on. You hear, they already
отключали уже включа Ты слышишь уже там
turned on the generator, zhuzhi
включили генератор жужи жи
zhizh, then already  Somehow it returned to normal, there
жит потом уже как-то нормализовалось не
were no power outages this year,
было перебоев со светом в этом году
somewhere in the spring, I think,
где-то по-моему весной вроде снова
somewhere again they hit the energy system of Ukraine, there
где-то лупили по энергосистеме Украины
were also power outages, but they were
тоже были перебои со светом но уже они
n’t felt like that anymore, Because for the first time
так не ощущались Потому что первый раз
then, suddenly people were like that. Damn.  And
тогда это внезапно люди такие А блин А
where is the light like A, how to turn on what? And
где свет типа А как включить что А
now, for example, we already have graphs. Yes,
сейчас уже например нас есть графики Да
if anything,
если что у
Nastya’s is now frozen now, frozen
Насти сейчас сейчас зависла зависла
Now wait, frozen now, now
Сейчас подождите зависла сейчас сейчас
developed, don’t turn off
развит не отключайте
[music]
[музыка]
so you can see Me  I can hear you,
так видно Меня на слышно да вас слышно
yes I can hear you Yes, yes, it’s visible, it turns out And now it’s
Да да да видно вот получается А сейчас
visible, it’s visible Yes, it’s just
видно видно видно Да просто немножко
slowing down a little while now it’s in
тормозит пока сейчас оно развес
weight now, as if we were there
получается сейчас как если вот были там
a couple of months ago, there was also a blackout,
пару месяцев назад тоже отключение света
but they’re on the schedule, you look, that is, yeah, the
но они по графику смотришь то есть ага
schedule won’t be here  it will be and everyone
график тут будет тут не будет и у всех
already has it, yes. For example, I also have
уже есть ю да У меня например есть также
special electric batteries there. Yes, they
там батареи специальные электрические Да
are charged, but while there is no light, you work with them,
заряженные а пока нету света ты с них
and you connected all these devices,
работаешь да подключил все эти приборы
and then the light turned on and charged, that’s
да потом включился свет и и зарядил вот
all. And it’s true that  our military there
всё А это правда что наши военные там
girls you have in Ukraine Yes, it’s true because
девочек у вас в Украине Да правда потому
it’s true Yes, the fact is that you can
что правда Да дело в том что ты можешь
see that even in Russia your
посмотреть что даже в России у вас ваши
military is doing a clean job, here in the Kursk
военные делают чист вот у вас в Курской
region now people have also started a riot
области сейчас люди тоже ж подняли бунт
and the authorities have already recognized Yes, uh
и власть уже признали Да что ээ
Russian military on the territory of the Kursk
российские военные на территории Курской
region were engaged in looting and
области занимались мародёрство
killing the civilian population of
занимались убийством мирного населения
their own Russians. Yes,
своих же русских Да
and also, look if they did this
и также да то смотри если они это делали
on their territory where your
на своей территории там где есть ваша
police are. And so on. But what can we
полиция И так дальше Да то что можно
say about those territories that were
говорить про те территории которые были
occupied by us?
оккупированы у нас например в Киевской
for example, in the Kyiv region there Bucha irpin there are still a lot of people who have been missing since 22 after the Russian occupation, do you understand what was done to them, where are they? Delhi Nobody knows. So, look how many people are writing from Donetsk. What, for example, is also chaos and this Girls are also scared to go there because yes, like Russian Soldiers and all sorts of Kadyrovites and Wagnerites And everyone who doesn’t want to go there, you know, can sing and what will she say that she  there she complains, they’ll kill her, that
она там пожалуется её прибьют вот и
’s all, so
всё поэтому
look if, uh, when in Russia
смотри если ээ вот когда в России
they say no, it can’t be that there is a
говорят нет не может быть чтобы там
Russian soldier engaged in violence,
солдат российский занимался насилием
look, they send a lot to us Yes, even
смотри а много отправляют у нас Да даже
besides look, except how much violence there is
кроме смотри кроме сколько есть насилия
in peacetime in Peacetime when there is
в мирно в Мирное время когда есть
police when here  you can get a sentence for this,
полиция когда вот можно получить за это
like yes And when a person strives
типа срок да А когда человек доры ется
for unlimited power Yes, when he
к безграничной власти Да когда у него
has a machine gun like yes He can come
есть автомат типа да Он может прийти
and kick out Kotya and in short Well, come on
ногой выбить и Котя и короче А ну давай
like and what does he do Therefore, if in  Peacetime There
типа и что делает Поэтому если в Мирное
is such a thing in such
время Такое есть то в такие
boundless times, then it
беспредельные времена то оно ещё хуже
turns out even worse, and that’s all horror, of course. And
получается вот и всё ужас конечно И да
yes, so look. The fact is that these are all
Так что и смотри Дело в том что эти все
people who are accustomed to cruelty. Yes, they
люди которые приучаются к жестокости Да
came, they want people in Ukraine, and
они пришли они хотят людей в Украине и
so on, they then  they return to
так дальше они же потом возвращаются в
Russia and they do all these atrocities
Россию так и они эти все бесчинства
in the cities, how many there are there that
делают в городах сколько есть там что
their hero killed someone, their hero or a
героя сво там убил кого-то герой сво или
schoolgirl, and so on, a bunch of other things.
школьницу и так дальше куча всего вот
Go to the news, kill your hero,
Заходите в новости убивайте героя свого
killed your hero, whole  a lot of stuff, that’s
убил героя свого целая куча всего вот и
all And then Russian society
всё И это потом российскому обществу
will have to sort it out Well, yes, but I
придётся это разгребать Ну это да Но я
still don’t understand why
до сих пор не понимаю почему
they’re sending it because there’s no one to
отправляют потому что мало некому
fight in the sense of no one And these people can be
воевать в смысле некому А этих можно
like, yes,
типа да
what will they do?
а что они сделают
Moreover, look how it turned out
Да больше того смотри как получилось
when the guy  they take a simple person in the twenty-
когда парня простого берут в двадцать
second year they took mobile phones Zro you in
втором году взяли мобили Зро вас в
Russia Yes, he is still
России Да он до сих пор
serving they got into prison He had to
служит забрались в тюрьмы Он должен был
serve 10 years he was taken from prison
сидеть 10 лет его забрали из тюрьмы
for six months he was
полгода он
released so look  so they turned around
свободу так смотри так они повернулись
Why should a simple guy fight until the
Почему парень простой должен воевать до
very end And in short, half is
самого конца А короче пол это
half a year and in short they were
полгода и короче их
released to the horse. Horror, and with admission it
отпустили коне Ужас а с поступлением
was also difficult, all the budget places
тоже было тяжело все места бюджетные
were given away by a student Yes, I heard
многие отдали отдали шника Да я слышал
when at Moscow State University there, for example, at the
когда в МГУ там например на Физический
FIFA Faculty of Physics there when they took  Yes, in the
факультет ФИФА там когда брали Да В
first medical school, all the budget places, in
первый МЕД все бюджетные места в
principle, everything was given to doctors for medical work,
принципе все на лечебное дело отдали
I also heard stories. Yes, what did the
лекам я тоже слышал истории Да что
guys do? Well, in general, with such
чуваки поступали Ну там вообще с такими
low scores, what are they like?  they
баллами эг низкими что ну как они там
will be able to study there
смогут
Yes, okay, there’s one last
Да окей есть ещё какой-то напоследок
question No, I didn’t understand, I’ll run away
вопрос Нет не понял хорошо побегу
Let’s say all the
Давайте всего
best to you too, thank you
хорошего вам тоже спасибо
very
Очень
interesting conversation, it started with the fact
интересный разговор да началась с того
that they were
что они
shining there,
там светили
they were fooling around and smoothly We moved from
это дурачились и плавно Мы перешли из
jokes to a serious conversation to serious
шуток на серьёзный разговор на серьёзные
conversations and it’s clear  that these Well, these are not children
разговоры и видно что эти Ну это не дети
anymore Yes, they are
уже Да взрослые они
adults It is clear that they think, it
совершеннолетние Видно что они думают
is clear that they think,
видно что думают
uh, sorry, propaganda, especially
вот э прость пропагандой особенно у
Nastya has more, Vika has less But in general, in
Насти больше у Вики меньше Но в целом в
general Yes, there is thinking, it is clear that they are thinking,
целом Да мышление есть видно мышление
it is clear that they understand  the reasons understand
видно что понимают они причины понимают
that
что как
it’s not Ukraine’s fault, yes,
бы это не Украина виновата да
but we
Но с
need to work with such categories
такими как бы категориями нужно работать
because look how they
потому что вот смотрите как они
repeat this one. What will we do and
повторяют вот этот А что мы сделаем а
what will we do? Yes, but we need to show
что мы сделаем Да но нужно показывать
that when people in the Kursk region
что когда людям в Курской области
got sick when they were left without  houses
припекло когда они остались без домов
like our Belgorod grandfather
как Белгородский дед наш
Yes, they started to rebel, they started
Да они начали бунтовать они начали там
shouting at the authorities there, that is, so far everything is
кричать на власть то есть пока всё
quiet with them And what will I do And what
тихонько у них они А что я сделаю А что
will I do No, I won’t do anything I’m
я сделаю Нет я же ничего не сделаю я
sitting in Novosibirsk I’m sitting in  In Moscow, I
сижу в Новосибирске Я сижу в Москве я
sit in irony, yes And when the war comes to
сижу в ирони да А когда война приходит в
his house,
его дом его
then his worldview somehow changes, the
тогда у него как-то меняется
Russian immediately begins to
мировоззрение россиянин сразу начинает
forget that nothing depends on him,
забывать что от него ничего не зависит
that he can’t do anything, he And what will
что он ничего не может он А что он
he do? He doesn’t think about it, they
сделает Он про это не думает они идут
start going  demand Give us payments
начинают требовать Дайте нам выплаты
Give us Stop the war Return
Дайте нам Остановите войну Верните
it Protect everything at once somehow when
сделайте защитите всё сразу как-то когда
the fried one pecks at the soft
жареный клюнул в мягкую
spot they immediately turn on
точку у них сразу включаются
democratic procedures that they can
демократические процедуры что они могут
somehow influence that’s why the first thing is
как-то повлиять вот поэтому первое что
necessary Yes, there is no need to be sorry
нужно Да не нужно жалеть людей в России
people in Russia, with their tacit consent, all this happens, including these girls. Yes, with their tacit consent, they can’t do anything, but if they had Moscow left without light, if they had one, would they really go out there? bonfires were burning in front of the city council that give us warmth yes And for now it doesn’t concern them but for them it’s far away The Kursk region felt the war about He doesn’t want war He doesn’t need it in Kyiv and Moscow hasn’t felt it yet and  all this talk that
почувствовала и все эти разговоры что от
nothing depends on us is an excuse,
нас ничего не зависит это отмазка
it’s like running away from responsibility.
это как бы убегание от ответственности
Because when you say that
Потому что когда ты говоришь что от меня
nothing depends on me, you do nothing.
ничего не зависит ты ничего не делаешь
Well, everything is fine. And when you say yes,
Ну всё да А когда ты говоришь да от меня
something depends on me. Then the question arises: A
что-то зависит Тогда стаёт вопрос А
why don’t you do anything if it’s up to you?
почему ты ничего не делаешь если от тебя
That is, you’re doing it on purpose
зависит То есть ты специально это
yes Or what Or you’re afraid you need to
делаешь да Или что Или ты боишься нужно
admit to yourself that either you’re afraid or
себе признаться что либо ты боишься либо
you don’t want to on purpose That’s why
ты специально не хочешь Вот поэтому
this is an evasion from
это есть убегание от
responsibility very good
ответственности очень хороший
conversation who watched it to the end Yes
разговор кто его досмотрел до конца Да
like  subscribe comment and send to your friends
лайк подписка комент и скиньте друзьям
Glory to Ukraine subscribe to th Telegram
Слава Украине подпишись на й Telegram
directly at once axis VN
прямо зараз ось ВН
apok tse more and more respectfully YouTube keeping
апок це дуже и дуже важливо YouTube заня
us busy through skargs Orcs in your ban and even
нас через скарги Орки в твый бан и дуже
more videos I don’t show people at the moment don’t
багато видео не показую людям вчасно не
show information about the stream For this
показуе информация про стрими Тому для
purpose, we need Mali operative  link to
того щоб ми Мали оперативний звязок
write directly at a time while there in telegra
пишиться прямо зараз а пок там в телегра
okm video  more tezh tsikava and korisna
окм видео ще теж цикава и корисна
information and we will
информация и мы повинни з вами тримати
show you the process YouTube Glory to
того чи покаже вам проце YouTube Слава
Ukraine
украини
letter
пись а